What makes this voice over film
ruinously bad?
>> They don't advertise for killers in a
newspaper.
That was my profession.
>> While this
>> As far back as I could remember, I
always wanted to be a gangster.
>> is one of cinema's most iconic openings.
>> To begin,
how to start?
>> In Adaptation [music] written by Charlie
Kaufman, a fictional version of Kaufman
is attempting to write the screenplay
[music] for the very movie we're
watching. After battling writer's block
for most of the film and making very
little progress, Charlie finds [music]
himself at a screenwriting seminar.
>> I'll start over. I need to face this
project head on.
>> And God help you if you use voice over
in your work, my friends. God help you.
>> This advice, [music] given by a
fictional version of Robert McKee, the
real author of one of the most renowned
screenwriting books of all time, [music]
>> Any idiot can write voice over
narration.
>> is not that much of an exaggeration of
the slightly more nuanced advice [music]
he gives in his book, where he still
calls voice over narration an indolent
practice and says [music] the trend
threatens the future of our art.
>> It's flaccid, sloppy writing.
>> There are plenty of reasons to be
skeptical of voice over.
>> And family photos, replicants didn't
have families, either.
>> Film is a largely visual medium, and
voice over can be used as a crutch to
deliver clunky exposition or reveal a
character's innermost landscape
>> I see myself from the outside.
>> instead of doing the difficult task
[music] of figuring out how to reveal
those things through a character's
actions or trusting the audience to pick
[music] up on the subtext that's on
screen. Lazy voice over can be one of
the most cringe-inducing forms of bad
writing [music] there is in movies.
>> Sushi, that's what my ex-wife called me.
>> So, I get why the advice to never use
voice over has become so common and why
so many people say they hate it, but
"threatens the future of our art" I find
it a little bit ridiculous because
>> I am unconcerned.
I am beyond their timid, lying morality.
>> Some of the best movies of all time use
over.
>> To me, it meant being somebody in a
neighborhood that was full of nobodies.
>> Some of my favorite film screenplays use
voiceover.
>> On a long enough timeline, the survival
rate for everyone drops to zero.
>> And I believe it can be used artfully to
help tell a story, just like any other
tool at a filmmaker's disposal. But what
separates the truly terrible from the
great? There's an extended cut of this
video with some longer examples
available on Nebula. If you want to
watch that version, click the link in
the description below. As McKee points
out, bad voiceover is redundant, lazy,
and overly expositional.
>> Whatever was in the bathtub was not
human.
Replicants don't have scales.
>> But then you have this.
>> You only loan a horse once.
And not to my opinion, [music] as long
as you're around, you should have it
nice.
>> When we talk about iconic voiceover,
>> [music]
>> Terrence Malick's second film, Days of
Heaven, is one of the first movies that
springs to my mind. It's hard to put a
finger on exactly why Linda Man's
childish, poetic ramblings work so well
throughout the film.
>> I met this guy named Ding-Dong.
He told me the whole earth is going up
in flames.
>> But maybe the magic is in its
authenticity, because it is, in effect,
childish, poetic ramblings. John Boorman
recounts the story of how this bit of
voiceover came about in his biography of
Malick. Apparently, Malick wanted Man's
to read the voiceover he had scripted.
But at the recording session, she was
much more interested in simply retelling
a Bible story she'd overheard where she
was staying.
>> There's going to be creatures running
every which way. [music] Some of them
burned after wings burned and
people are going to be screaming and
hollering for help.
>> Malick ended up loving her off-the-cuff
storytelling so much they basically just
played the whole movie for her and let
her riff over top.
>> He was tired of living like the rest of
them, nosing around like a pig in a
gutter.
>> And then, took bits of voice over they
liked and painstakingly painted them
throughout the film wherever they
worked. Sometimes playing a single line
on loop through the entire movie to find
the perfect fit.
>> It figures that some people need more
than they got.
Other people got more than they need.
Just a matter of getting us all
together.
>> What makes this voice over work so well
is that it's not just being treated as a
way to convey information or exposition.
Instead, Malick applies the same
artistic process of discovery to the
voice over that he uses for every other
part of the film. And he allows
Lindeman's offbeat ramblings to shape
the tone and texture of the movie, which
toes a line between innocence and
something more foreboding, even in its
imagery.
This kind of vague poetic connection
between the voice over and the plot
wouldn't work for every movie, but
what's most important here is that this
approach to the voice over complements
the overall feeling and style of the
movie. And this is one of the biggest
things that I think sets great voice
over apart from the bad. Voice over has
a unique power to set the tone of a
film.
>> Everything's a copy of a copy of a copy.
>> Whether it's the stumbling first lines
of The Big Lebowski,
>> Well,
I lost my train of thought here.
But,
yeah,
hell.
I done introduced him enough.
>> the stoned haziness of Joanna Newsom's
voice over for Inherent Vice,
>> Does it ever end?
Of course it does.
It did.
>> Or the austere, detached, almost history
documentary style of Michael Hordern's
narration for Barry Lyndon.
>> The United Kingdom was in a state of
great excitement from the threat
generally accredited of a French
invasion.
>> Whoever's performing the voice over
essentially becomes the voice of the
movie, and the qualities of that actor
specific voice along with the emotional
tenor of the performance has a huge
influence on how the overall film ends
up feeling. If the reading of the
voiceover feels dry, lifeless, or forced
in any way, the movie itself ends up
feeling lifeless as well. So, it's a
tool that must be used with care. But
when it works,
it can be magical.
>> He installed himself in a rocking chair
and smoked a cigar down in the evenings
[music] as his wife wiped her pink hands
on an apron and reported happily on
their two children.
>> It's the specific blend of voiceover,
imagery, and score that really lingers
in my mind when I think back on the
assassination of Jesse James by the
coward Robert Ford.
>> They didn't even know their father's
name.
>> Like with Days of Heaven, this voiceover
also came about as the result of a happy
accident. I'd always wondered who this
voiceover was. It's not a recognizable
actor, but it has such a unique quality.
And while flipping through Roger
Deakins' new book, I was delighted to
learn it's actually one of the film's
editors. Hugh Ross had recorded himself
reading the voiceover as a temporary
placeholder to edit to, and director
Andrew Dominik ended up loving his
reading so much that they kept it for
the final film. Voiceover inherently
breaks the film away from strict
realism. That's only bad if you think
realism is somehow inherently the best
stylistic approach to filmmaking. If the
formal narrative presentation of the
film is more theatrical or stylized in
some way, then voiceover can be a very
effective tool. I find the best uses of
voiceover lean into what makes narrated
stories interesting. There are a couple
ways you can do this. Sometimes, like in
The Royal Tenenbaums, the voiceover is
presented as if it is the literal
reading of [music] a book.
>> Royal Tenenbaum bought the house on
Archer Avenue in the winter of his 35th
year.
>> Which is maybe not that interesting if
the movie is actually a book, but it
adds a layer of meta irony and creates
an interesting framing device for the
film when that book is fictional.
>> No one in his family had spoken to him
in 3 years.
>> When what has felt like an omniscient
narrator shows up halfway through The
Big Lebowski,
>> We got a good sarsaparilla.
>> Sioux City sarsaparilla?
>> Yeah, it's a good one.
>> We almost get the sense that the Dude is
coming into contact with God himself. In
Sunset Boulevard, the narrator is dead,
somehow speaking to us from the great
beyond. And in Double Indemnity,
>> Yes, I remembered.
Just like I remembered what you had told
me, Keyes.
>> The voiceover takes the form of a
confession.
>> How there was no getting off till the
end of the line.
Where the cemetery was.
>> Or the narration can lean into a more
deliberately literary quality, making
use of interesting language. [music]
>> But once he perceived that he would
never see Jesse again,
>> [music]
>> Frank would be wrought up,
perplexed,
despondent.
>> Sure, film might be a visual medium, but
when you use narration, you suddenly
have the entire world of artistic and
stylistic possibility that literary
writing provides.
>> But what [music] does a doctor avail in
a contest with the grim, invincible
enemy?
>> Everything that can give language in a
book an interesting style can now be
applied to the voiceover. Whatever the
approach, most great voiceover feels a
little inherently theatrical.
The characters may not speak naturally,
but they aren't just robotically reading
the details of the plot. They're telling
a tale, performing a story for the
audience. The more casual ramblings of
Linda in Days of Heaven leaves you
feeling like you might be one of the
workers sitting across the fire from her
after a day of working in the fields.
>> You figure there must be something wrong
with them,
the way they always got no luck.
>> The same goes for Newsom's narration in
Inherent Vice, where it feels like we
might be listening to her spin a yarn at
the very restaurant the character
appears at in the film.
>> Oh man, oh man, never be surprised
[music] at the levels of disrespect
within the LAPD.
>> You might be noticing that much of what
makes great voiceover is similar to what
makes good writing or good performance.
And as with both, it's best to show
instead of tell. Wait. How can voiceover
be used to show? Isn't it inherently
telling?
To me,
being a gangster was better than being
president of the United States.
>> Goodfellas leans heavily on voiceover
from the main character, Henry Hill.
>> In the summer when they played cards all
night, nobody ever called the cops.
>> is essentially framed as a story we're
being told by Henry himself, and the
voiceover is lyrical, inventively
written, and helps us understand the
world of the mobsters. But if it was
just that, I don't think it would work
that well. What really brings the
voiceover in Goodfellas to life is not
what Henry is telling us, it's what the
way he tells the story is showing us.
>> I mean, at 13, I was making more money
than most of the grown-ups in the
neighborhood. I mean, I had more money
than I could spend. I had it all.
>> The advice to show rather than tell
originally comes from literature, but
when it's applied to film, it's easy to
think it means literally using images on
the screen to show something rather than
using words. But I think that's the
wrong way to interpret the advice.
Instead, show don't tell isn't trying to
drive us away from using words, it's
guiding us away from simply stating or
explaining what's going on with a
character, a major theme, or a
development in the plot with those
words.
>> Replicants weren't [music] supposed to
have feelings.
Neither were Blade Runners.
What the hell was happening to me?
>> Instead, what's usually more engaging
for the audience is to reveal important
details and character revelations in the
subtext of what's being said,
essentially allowing us to read between
the lines. And the voiceover in
Goodfellas is incredibly rich with
subtext. Towards the end of the film,
Henry speaks directly to us, the
audience, from the witness stand. And
there's a way in which this recasts the
entire film as a confession. All of that
stands in interesting contrast to the
almost loving, nostalgic way Henry
describes his life as a gangster.
>> And when the cops, they assigned the
whole army to stop Jimmy, what did he
do?
>> How's it going, Joe? Good.
>> He made them partners.
>> Okay.
>> If this is really Henry reflecting back
on this life, we can understand through
the way he romanticizes the world of the
mob while glossing over many of the more
horrific details that we see
that he hasn't really learned a lesson
at all. He isn't actually repenting of
any wrongdoing.
>> That's when I knew I would never have
come back from Florida alive.
>> He's just using this confession to
escape consequences while he continues
to see himself as better than those
outside the life. That use of voiceover
is also an example of voiceover as
counterpoint, which is one of the few
acceptable uses that McKee mentions. If
redundant voiceover, which just restates
what you're already seeing or what is
obvious to the viewer is the ultimate
sin, then it makes sense that voiceover,
which does the opposite of that by
providing contrasting information or
tone, is one of the ways you can make
voiceover more effective.
>> He claimed that as long as you're
playing for keeps and the law's coming
at you, it's considered okay to shoot
all witnesses.
You had to take the consequences though
and not whine about it later.
>> Here's an example from Eric Rohmer's
movie Love in the Afternoon.
>> Puis, l'humeur de Chloé, ça se
A story about a married man for whom the
worst problem in his life is just how
many beautiful women there are in Paris.
Through the film, he occasionally
narrates what he's feeling or thinking
as the story progresses.
Which wouldn't really add that much
except that Rohmer uses this to
illustrate the way this character is
creating a false internal narrative to
justify his own actions. As he starts
letting himself slip into an affair with
an old ex who shows up at his work,
through the voiceover, the character
paints himself as interacting with her
very reluctantly and even fearfully. But
the attentive viewer will notice that
this is total BS.
As viewers, we're seeing one thing play
out in the character on screen, but the
voiceover provides an ironic
counterpoint to what we're seeing,
trapping us inside the character's own
self-deluding narrative.
Finally, voiceover has to be treated as
one of the instruments in the orchestra.
It has to harmonize with everything
else. Part of what makes the voiceover
from the opening of Goodfellas or this
opening segment from Sentimental Value
work so well
is the way the rhythm and flow of the
narration, the language of the script,
the music, and editing are all
seamlessly working together to create a
whole that is greater than the sum of
its parts. Great voice over doesn't need
all of the attributes we've talked
about, but if you examine bad voice
over, you'll usually notice it's missing
most of them. The actual writing of the
voice over is uninventive, the
performance might feel forced, or
doesn't have a sense of motivation or
perspective, or has a tone that clashes
with the rest of the film. The narrative
frame of where the voice over is coming
from is either uninteresting or unclear,
or the flow of images and voice over
together simply isn't satisfying. Voice
over is hard to get right, but that
doesn't mean it's bad. If anything, the
advice should be it's a very powerful
storytelling device,
so use it wisely. If you're not sure if
it's working, it might be better to just
leave it out.
But done well, it's just another way to
do what movies do best.
Tell a story. A lot of what I've learned
about filmmaking and the research I do
for these videos comes from the film
books that I read. If you want to see an
in-depth tour of many of my favorite
books on my bookshelf, I made a two-part
series where I'd break down my
recommendations and what I took away
from each book. You can watch these
videos exclusively on Nebula. Nebula is
a streaming service created by creators
like myself, and there's a lot of great
things you'll get when you sign up. In
addition to exclusive videos I've made
like my bookshelf's tour, you can also
see all of my videos early and without
any ads or sponsor reads. It's not just
my videos you'll find an extensive
library of other creators on there,
including other great video essayists
like Broey Da Chanel, Like Stories of
Old, Cinema Stix, or Patrick Willems.
Myself and many of these creators have
exclusive videos and content on Nebula
that you can't see anywhere else, and
Nebula's was putting out new incredible
originals that I think you'll enjoy,
including my favorite travel game show
Jetlag and Patrick H. Willems wonderful
new short film The Dinner Plan. Nebula
is super affordable. If you visit
go.nebula.tv/thomasflight,
you'll get 50% off the annual plan,
making it just $2.50 a month or $30 a
year. There's of course a link in the
description below you can click or use
the QR code on the screen. Go check out
Nebula, sign up, browse the exclusive
videos I have available along with all
the other great original content on the
platform. Thanks so much to those who
have signed up and watch on Nebula.
Watching on there goes a long way to
support my work and the work of other
incredible creators. And thanks to
Nebula for sponsoring this video. Again,
go to go.nebula.tv/thomasflight
to get 50% off today.